George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok 1921-1940
ML31.A59
Antheil, George, 1900-1959
Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1876-1970
approximately 500 items 3 containers 2.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
George Antheil was a composer, pianist, author, and inventor. He first gained fame and notoriety in the 1920s for his mechanistic compositions. This collection principally consists of letters between George Antheil and his longtime patron, Mary Louise Curtis Bok. Other items include several writings by Antheil, photographs of his staged works, promotional materials, and clippings.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Antheil, George, 1900-1959--Correspondence.; Antheil, George, 1900-1959--Criticism and interpretation.; Antheil, George, 1900-1959.; Antheil, George, 1900-1959.; Antheil, George, 1900-1959. Antheilized notation.; Friede, Donald--Correspondence.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972--Correspondence.; Sternberg, Constantin von, 1852-1924--Correspondence.; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971--Correspondence.; Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1876-1970--Correspondence.; Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1876-1970.; Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1876-1970. George Antheil correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok. 1921-1940.
Subjects
Composers--United States--Correspondence.
Titles
George Antheil collection, 1921-1940
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Mrs. Cary William Bok, 1975.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Other Repositories
Additional materials can be found in the UCLA Performing Arts Special Collections and the New York Public Library.
Related Material
The Music Division holds numerous special collections that contain Antheil correspondence, including the
George and Böske Antheil Papers
George Antheil Correspondence to Stanley Hart
Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Collection; Irving Schwerké Collection
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection
Percy Aldridge Grainger Collection
Serge Koussevitzky Archive
Leonard Bernstein Collection
Aaron Copland Collection
and the
Modern Music Archives
. A small quantity of cataloged letters are available in ML 95.A726.
Access and Restrictions
The George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Mary Louise Curtis Bok, founder of the Curtis Institute of Music, served as patron to George Antheil throughout much of his career. Antheil first made the acquaintance of Bok in 1921 through former theory and composition teacher Constantin von Sternberg. Despite her generous financial support, Bok was not, as she wrote in a letter to Antheil dated April 13, 1931, "in sympathy with the so-called modern trend," and generally disapproved of Antheil's music. Antheil dedicated a number of his musical works to Bok, including Night Piece, Six Little Pieces for String Quartet, and Symphonie in Fa.
Scope and Content Note
The George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok spans the period 1921-1940. The primary series consists chiefly of letters and telegrams between the composer and his patron. Correspondence between Bok and others regarding Antheil, namely Ezra Pound, Donald S. Friede, and Constantin von Sternberg, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Clippings and other enclosures are scattered among these materials. Additional items of note include a letter from Pound to Antheil and a telegram from Igor Stravinsky to the composer.
"Writings" contains two substantive, titled works by Antheil. Antheilcized Notation, or, Music for everybody who can tell one from two and two from three provides an explanation of the composer's intriguing "See-Note" method of piano pedagogy. This subject is described at great length in the George and Böske Antheil Papers, as well. The second work, Many Thoughts to M.L.B. and a Key to My Music (To Be Remembered While Listening to It), is a reproduction of a lengthy piece enclosed in Antheil's February 1926 letter to Bok. "Miscellany" comprises assorted newspaper clippings, promotional materials, and photographs of the Transatlantic sets by Ludwig Sievert. These items are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Organization of the George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok
The George Antheil Correspondence with Mary Louise Curtis Bok is organized in 3 series:
Correspondence, 1921-1940
Writings, undated
Miscellany, 1927-1930
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561030
Container List
- Correspondence, 1921-1940 (Box 1-2)
  Letters and telegrams with enclosures, sent and received. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - Antheil, George
    - 1921-1930 (Box-folder 1/1-14)
    - 1931-1940 (Box-folder 2/1-13)
  - Erskine, John
    - Erskine to Antheil, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Friede, Donald S.
    - Friede to Antheil and Bok, 1927 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Graf, Herbert
    - 1930 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Hammer, Mrs. William C.
    - Hammer to Antheil, Bok, and John Erskine1932 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Hanson, Martin H.
    - 1922-1929 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Hofmann, Josef
    - 1927 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Konzertdirektion Leonard
    - 1923 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Lucas, Clarence
    - 1927 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Pound, Ezra
    - Pound to Bok and Antheil, 1923-1927 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Reiner, Fritz
    - 1927 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Robinson, Lennox
    - Robinson to Antheil, 1928 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Sternberg, Constantin von
    - 1921 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Stokowski, Leopold
    - Stokowski to Antheil and Bok, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Stravinsky, Igor
    - Stravinsky to Antheil, 1922, undated (Box-folder 2/27)
- Writings, undated (Box 3)
  - Antheilcized notation, or, Music for everybody who can tell one from two and two from three, undated, Holograph manuscript; [5] p. (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Many thoughts to M.L.B. and a Key to my music (to be remembered while listening to it), undated, Holograph manuscript; [10] p. (Box-folder 3/1)
- Miscellany, 1927-1930 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1927, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Programs, 1927 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Transatlantic, undated, 4 black and white photographs, 1 negative; Images by Ludwig Siefert (Box-folder 3/4)